welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
okay all right so welcome to the stoah
this is the mediation campfire usually
hosted by myself and Jason and often
also accompanied by by Peter for those
of you who don't have the background on
what the the frame of this this regular
meetup is I'll give a quick little
description but we also should have
descriptions on the website and I think
that we've also I think that Peter has
also hosted a document or link to a
document that kind of has a bunch of
information phrases and definitions for
what media mimetic mediation is but it
was basically a phrase coined in the
culture war 2.0 paper that Peter and and
Colin or Peter in Connor Barnes written
and published that we got really popular
and the way that you know we don't have
a go any kind of solid definition on it
but Jason and I prefer to like very
quickly summarize it as the medic
mediation being what happens in between
the tribes so kind of the connective
tissue so that we are sharing insights
seeing each other and benefiting from
all the plurality of perspectives that
we have and ideologies and and
philosophies and spiritualities and
whatnot so yeah I like this space in
between metaphor because it does give us
a little bit of it just genuinely has a
different orientation than any existing
tribe it's the tribe with no barriers or
no boundaries
and I like that it's kind of a
provocative image
I was thinking earlier this morning
about what I might speak to I do have a
a a specific frame that I could bring to
this and it's actually kind of centers
around the role of order and chaos in
this whole space if yeah I mean I could
I could go there it's a bit you know and
ordering chaos is what it would be
framed I think especially from kind of a
Western philosophical play space but if
we're looking at it from a you know
something more Eastern like a Buddhist
lens this would be the difference
between form and emptiness or emptiness
and or openness I like a little bit
better of a translation and I see these
dynamics is like kind of essential to
the whole inner workings but that being
said before I dive in I was also
wondering maybe if there's anything
specific that anybody wants to hit on
and I might be able to kind of tie that
into some of my opening thoughts before
we're off to the races because the
majority of this I'd like to just be a
kind of group exploration last time we
started a very ground level within the
individual kind of felt sense of
embodying this mediation rule the time
before that it was a lot more high-level
we were talking about different kind of
memetic tribal wars and stuff like that
and ended up slowly kind of working our
way down a little bit more into the
individual level but was wondering you
know anybody come here looking for or
you know a certain certain lens a
certain angle questions that that seem
very very unknown or you know very very
alive in your experience when talking
about thematic radiation
can I ask something yeah first hi i'm
i'm ryan it's my first time joining the
group and nice nice to meet everyone so
I didn't really understand like what
nomadic mediation like what like where
are people doing the mediations
basically I wasn't sure what platform or
form it took uh sorry if this is kind of
inappropriate or like off the rail or
whatever but I kind of I asked some of
the questions on the slack group and
never received an answer so I kind of
want to show up and ask like um like
world the mediations actually happening
like I I'm a mediator and I work for an
organization police natural mediation in
Gresham Oregon and that's kind of my set
up but I was curious for other well is
it for other people mmm I mean I could
guess I'd love to you know speak about
from my perspective on it and I think
Jason and I are a little bit more a more
oriented toward this in the sense that
we see or a mediation mediation as being
kind of a general orientation or
perspective to bring to any and all
conversations that were thrown into you
know so Jason and I have a podcast where
the the two of us co-host and and have
guests on and and we kind of always kind
of keep this the spirit of the mimetic
mediation in the background or as a core
intention but it's not extremely
explicit or well you know we don't have
any kind of specific psycho technologies
or frameworks that were regularly
employing I do know that Peter on the
other hand seems to be exploring what
mimetic mediation would look like for
specific conversation modalities so this
might be circling practices or emotional
what it was there's a number of
different conversation modalities that
like kind of are very well structured
you know restating somebody what
somebody's perspective that were not
familiar with
making sure that both of you agreed
before you move forward and so I know
he's played a little bit more with like
the structure that we could actually
create and and part of what we see this
convert these conversations these weekly
conversations as being is like finding
opportunities to find places to do
mediation and so so yeah and because
it's so the phrase itself is so kind of
nebulous Jason and I haven't done
anything very structured with it but but
yeah rather see it it's just kind of a
core intention and but yeah and we'd
love to also figure out how you know
maybe the future sessions like this we
invite you know some people who have
genuine different genuinely different
perspectives and try and figure out how
how to host that and and create a space
that allows the mediation to arise in
those conversations as well so yeah I
don't know if that completely answers
the question but that's my perspective
at least and ads and stuff yeah so so so
and if my perspective comes from where I
am in life so I am an Orthodox Jew
living in Israel and for me what
medication kinda means is that when I
employ in different situations so I
represent different populations so um
Peter and the food also have this
article called the marginal figure which
I kind of I think I do actually
recognize myself as being that which is
kind of a person who goes in between
different cultures and groups so what
that kind of means is that so when I'm
here right in this very multicultural
environment so I feel that much like a
representative of my tribe which is kind
of a relatively conservative traditional
community very religious also Jewish I
live in Israel so I don't know about
Zionism exactly identify with that fake
complex for me but definitely that's
part of what I represent at least
towards other people and kind of
bringing my own perspective here to a
multicultural group and also in Israel
so I'm in the features college and I am
in part of program that has multiple all
different teachers colleges in Israel
together so their secular religion
some of them are Arab colleges they
speak in Arabic and they're so they're
Muslim - Muslim attended one Christian
and so as bringing the perspective of a
medic mediator when these meetups come
up I tried it I kind of see a drive to
bring the conversation away just from
strictly education and also try to have
people bring up their perspectives and
what's going deep inside them kind of
addressing the elephant in the room and
almost raising the conflict that it
could be addressed and having people
exposed to the perspectives that kind of
want to be spoken about keep speaking
about pedagogy instead of talking about
how people feel regarding everything so
that's kind of how I kind of see it as
trying to have people to express their
culture and where they're coming from
and kind of bring me to the table and I
say that's my role because I find myself
in that position anytime
I love it yeah and I know a lot of
people have been on a number of these
calls so if anybody else feels inclined
to yeah there's no right answer here of
what medic mediation is so if it means
something to you I'd love to hear more
but the personal reflections I've got a
personal reflection last night I was
sitting around the campfire with my
family and so I saw like my Nana and
Papa who I haven't seen in well over a
month and so they were like ready they
find they're like okay guys come for a
fire like we'll have a social distance
campfire it'll be okay because they've
been pretty conservative and protecting
themselves so we went out there and then
I had an uncle there and my parents were
there and I noticed people were sharing
things that they had been hearing like
conspiracy theories and other like
political narratives and things that I
would never have expected them to have
been exposed to and all of a sudden I
had this scent like this sense that was
realization that even these my
grandparents I thought were not
susceptible to like all of these
different things meaning like I didn't I
don't see them their tribe is just their
family and like their neighbors and the
people they work with but now all of a
sudden I see how there's these other
mimetic tribes that they can find and
then lean into and so that's where I
find this being like most relevant to me
is like sitting around my family and all
of these contradicting ideas and things
come up and you feel a conversation
heating up and I'm just like how this
temptation to share all of my opinions
but I'm like no like I don't want to do
that here like what is the way for me to
be to just to love my family the best
actually and so yeah and really for me
it feels like I'm just mediating between
myself and my own triggered responses
and my family so that's um yeah one way
this is really relevant for me yeah I
will say I mean this is a good reminder
to the the reason we chose the medic or
campfire is because we expect the
dialogue to kind of embody that or Oreo
strive to embody that kind of
orientation right these these campfires
like there's such a kind of closeness a
shared aspect to them a warmth like
everybody's kind of huddled around kind
of enjoying the same source of warmth so
it's just like this conviviality is just
kind of inherent in what it's like to be
at a campfire and that very much is kind
of one of the core metaphors or lenses
that we kind of see these conversations
taking as well so another thing to kind
of be aware as now yeah just this kind
of just human human to human very primal
kind of perspective sharing the fire
here I know that you had your mic
unmuted for a second could I could I
call on you yeah I well I was just going
to say I could relate I think I shared
in the chat I can relate to both what
Benjamin shared and what Tyler shared of
you know being someone who can kind of
exist between tribes and you know has
that you know it's like and then wanting
to you know kind of up level my skill
when it comes to being able to sit with
the discomfort that comes from conflict
with family like my husband and I are in
a discussion right now about gun control
and it's that there's a lot of feelings
around that and so like just being able
to like hold space for it you know I
like the phrase hold space of you know
for what's happening with me what's
happening with him what's happening for
the you know collective you know the the
relationship and I see that if something
I can take into not just you know with
him but it's something that like I
practice with him on a daily basis you
know there's always those things that
come up but you know being able to come
here and have a conversation and
like I wanted to put it out to like put
out a question for the group which was
like how do you how do you work with the
big emotions that come up when somebody
says something that like is totally
totally outside of your perspective and
you know there's big feet and for me I
have big feelings that come up when
somebody says something that is totally
like antithetical to what I think and
how do I not have those you know that
instantaneous get reaction of well
that's just stupid which can you know
I've gotten there and I don't do that
one but there's other ones and so I was
curious for the for the rest of the
group how they how they work with those
that that you know those strong
reactions that come up
you
I think sometimes these things are
really easy to talk about in theory and
when you're in the moment we all default
to you know the fighter flight or freeze
I believe that any time we can reflect
physiological sensation and say I mean
it sounds kind of cheesy but I think
that if we're grounding it and they here
and now and your relation to the the
space and time that you're holding with
someone you say you know what you said
kind of makes my stomach kind of jittery
or my heart just jumped a couple of
palpitations and I think it's because
you stated such such and such and I
believe this way those are some ways
that I've kind of dealt with those
situations just because it kind of it
takes some of the edge off of what you
have to say your response so definitely
these are the very difficult situations
but sometimes what I try to do is I mean
if what someone said is very even if
it's very outrageous I guess being human
we do get reactions but if we try to ask
them questions like why they said this
and where they're going from maybe we
can understand their view of the truth
because I believe that everyone has a
different view reality that's how I try
to do it very unsuccessfully
I would add kind of one thing that that
I think is you know we've in some of
these previous conversations we talked a
lot about how like getting in touch with
the felt sense is important and doing
the decoupling from the ideas is also
important because the idea is kind of
they kind of justify the emotional
reaction and then another component here
too is we I think we even used it or use
the phrase of kind of getting caught up
or constricted into that response you
know it's like we feel like there's no
other way to react other than some sort
of you know fight flight or response or
or freeze one of the things that's kind
of interesting or a move here and kind
of bringing up the space in between
again is that emotions have so much
harder they have such a harder time
evolving or processing or dissipating if
there's no space for them to dissipate
into and so sometimes like the most
simple thing and I think this is even
like a cognitive behavioral therapy
technique is to like literally become
aware of the room that the space the
room that you're in you know you can
kind of be like up there's a you know
there's that wall here's this there's an
empty space in between and just kind of
expanding your cognition does kind of
strangely its you know create some space
around this very solid constricted
emotional response and it's somehow like
it tends to dissipate and this is like
one of the one of the most interesting
things is that you can both do this with
negative and positive emotions and the
fascinating thing is that usually I and
the intention year is important in the
sense that if you're doing it to make it
go away within this agenda of it going
away probably dangerous territory you
know you know it's like telling the kid
not to eat the cookie
but but if you do it from like just
genuinely opening things up and getting
a sense of the larger picture negative
emotions tend to kind of dissipate into
space
they kind of dissolve and positive ones
tend to expand which is a quite the
optimistic thing very optimistic
observation or something like that I
suppose but yeah and you could do this
in your own body as well because I think
sometimes if your your emotional
reaction is extremely localized you can
also find another part of your body that
doesn't have any kind of constriction
and notice the difference between the
two and that creates some space as well
but you know the room in space around
you I found probably a little bit more
accessible because sometimes the body is
just too too excited or something just
one of the techniques are too abstract
for me and this could just feel my own
personal tendency like I would really
like to see like you people here have I
take a severe disagreement got them like
fleshing it out or something like that
like or me even like a tangible cases
that people have experience kind of just
to see what that would be like because I
feel like there's a lot of this abstract
talk and for me yeah I guess I don't I
guess I just avoid conflict most of the
time and so I don't hit it head-on or
there in situations where it's fleeting
it's not like a full-out conversation I
kind of would like to see what what
happened nothing she is right now but I
kind of what happen if you put two
people in two different a different
tribes just try to like talk about
anything together and like what would
happen when people connect would there
be short wires would it be like oh maybe
just never talked that's why they don't
get along if they would ever just like
things would be fine I'm really in case
people have experiences seeing this or
living it
I mean I could try to create a
disagreement if you watch because like I
I personally don't really have a very
strong view but so I'm from Karachi
Pakistan and our country so we cannot
with visit Israel so Israel is the only
country that is not accepted or like we
don't consider Israel as a country and
that's why we cannot get visas and like
from what I've heard so this is also
completely based off media information
online from what I've heard is that
Israel as a territory is slowly taking
over Palestine so all of it was
Palestine before and Israel is doing
injustice and expanding their territory
so I would love to hear your views on it
well so I would I'm totally up for this
if other people want to do this right
now I know this is like cific there you
go wanna go can go very concrete if you
want to this items do this just two
things one definitely not recorded and
two I have to say I am like even
knowledgeable so much on the topic but
just from my own I can say what I know
from from what I know from right road
so people after that I'm totally open
and I'd like to leave it out for some
sort of decision because this is a
little bit different a medic mediation
kind of bring me to a very specific
mediation so I say go for it here is it
jumping into the deep end of the
swimming pool it from my perspective
might be useful to put in some ground
rules like if we want to do some mimetic
mediation when could we intervene maybe
allow us some space in between the
exchange for us to intervene and
translate or whatever
yeah well let me it sounds like we're
pro I'm gonna pause the recording so we
can maybe then restart it after we've
done that yeah then this exploring if
it's possible or whatever so I'll do
that now
alright we are back on air so yeah I saw
Benjamin thanks for taking the plunge
and you know being being kind of laying
yourselves both vulnerable in front of
everybody as we watch you foreigner from
our computers and yeah I think that
takes a ton of courage to to talk about
things and and you know the the your two
perspectives I think are some of the
most kind of pronounced versions of of
the you know the the genuine danger in
some instances of being able to dialogue
with people who who come from different
different perspectives different
cultural backgrounds and yeah so thank
you for being quite quite brave one
thing kind of quick observation I would
say you know as Benjamin said wasn't
extremely conflict oriented and I think
that's likely due to the fact that
you're at a mediation campfire and and
obviously are kind of modeling a lot of
the qualities that I think embody what
mediation is the one that was kind of a
most palpable to me was the fact that
when we kind of find ourselves in a
mediation role it requires us to hold
multiple perspectives or I like the more
general phrase of reference points as we
proceed and and the toughest part about
that is it it is inherently ambiguous
because they disagree with each other
like no two references points can
completely agree and especially when
we're in kind of emotionally and
historically charged space
so much of what the mediator is doing is
kind of like you know they're their
burden is is being able to hold
conflicting perspectives in in their in
their experience and it's genuinely kind
of you know I think it came up a few
times like you know I don't want to
speak for these all these people because
because I can't and and the fact that we
even know that though you know that is
one of the most essential qualities here
to know that when considering others we
can only partially consider them and we
can kind of play act and approximate
their position but but yeah being okay
with ambiguity kind of nebulosity it's
kind of an inherent skill that I think
SP Boyd here and and yeah you guys kind
of did that amazingly and then you know
the other big thing here too is like
even in these conversations well we
might not have had like a direct
mediation and I think another important
part that's come up multiple times it's
like not every mimetic mediation every
time we're acting from a medication we
don't need to arrive at some sort of
conclusion it's an ongoing process and
I'm sure that both of you will after
this conversation go talk to some of
your friends that may be a little bit
you know the old its display some of
this conversation and light ways and
kind of say like yeah it was really
weird how much we related and you know
we we could explore experiencing very
similar emotions on both sides of the
fence and and so yeah like I actually
think mediation was happening here even
though it's in it's more subtle kind of
long game form so it's something that I
think is always kind of good to keep in
mind so that being said my reflections
I'd love to hear if anybody else has
anything if you do have to drop off at
any time of course we are over time so
please do so but yeah I think but kind
of my last thoughts and thanks again and
yeah I'm going to open it up and see if
anybody else had anything that they
wanted to share
I'll say wanting small even I spoke so
much already but um just I I feel like
what really helps me do this was the
fact that this was I committed mimetic
mediators group and whenever there's
people around anions I always like
everybody you always feel judged but
here I felt like what was gonna be
judging me it was not going to be at all
how politically know how and
historically know how I was but kind of
how comes like how human I could be
because almost like like as a boy I was
know things now but like how vulnerable
I would be would be like are you really
being authentic and vulnerable and I
wondered how that would affect even like
the hardest people really like so you
know these people here around you they
don't really care what what was right
and wrong they just want to see help
human you can be I think that even
someone like the hardcore people of mine
of my tribe would be when you push by
that
yeah I just wanted to say thank you
because that was there was a lot I
learned just in terms of experiences
I've had
Benjamin hearing you are Benjamin Hassan
hearing you guys articulate that helped
me understand some different different
experiences I've had and so I yeah it
was just truly appreciated that I got to
be part of this and and here you guys do
that thank you
yeah I just want to say to you I thank
you I appreciate that and and I did one
call but Benjamin before I know a couple
times you expressed a desire for a
little bit more heat and a little bit
more passion fire and I do that I do
think that that could be helpful given
that in a lot of these real life
situations will not be we will not have
Luxuria but my medic mediation
comforting environment so I think that
can be more that can be helpful to
practice in terms of um replicating a
real-life situation and this is my first
time but uh I was I was hoping that the
way that we did this today was like a
regular thing and damiano and I are
really passionate about this and have
talked about this for hours and hours
and hours so um I was curious if in the
future people are interested in doing
more of these and also doing more
intense you know conversations around
very heated controversial topics and if
that was something people were
interested in and and if and even if we
didn't want to have it on this call if
people interested another one if that
wasn't appropriate for the Sunday
morning but um yeah I just did something
dis impossible I'll just say that I've
Jared and I had had a conversation and
I've talked to Peter and we're in having
conversations about creating something
called like an emotional emotional
conflict dojo so like a situation where
you know starting at a you know picking
a topic that's you know kind of very
benign like toilet paper over or under
and like escalating from there and
getting to the place where you could
talk you know getting a bunch of people
to a place where you could get into a
you know sparring you know could start
sparring with each other on these topics
and so that's something that like I
think there's conversations happening
about trying to make something like that
happen at just adding on tech here's
Benjamin and I are already in
discussions around inventing mediator
games that we could play out in slack
and and zoom so highly recommend joining
this
there's a channel called the stoah and
if you're interested helping us just
some game design there and taking it
online
yeah and I'll also echo so yeah Ryan
this is a weekly thing so we're always
meeting it's been completely different
each time I think some of people have
been to all of them and and and yeah
I've actually you know Jason Peter and I
were kind of sending messages and back
forth and we floated a bunch of
different ideas but but we do have a bit
of a it sounds like we all are kind of
conspiring to see from the stoah
community because we have such a diverse
selection of thinkers and its diverse
enough that we actually even know that
there are certain thinkers that have
kind of like publicly disagreed and kind
of sparked at different times so we have
also been kind of thinking about how we
might be able to invite them to this
session to kind of you know maybe maybe
do some some live mediation with a with
an audience and I don't know if yeah the
the specifics of it that aren't there
but yeah I know that intention is there
too because we do want to kind of really
get in the into things at first and
thanks to Benjamin for for pulling the
trigger
[Laughter]
all right well any other last thoughts I
think well this is a good place it
sounds like we're in a good place to
wrap up here as usual the really really
pause instead of continuing thoughts no
you go it's cool I wanna hear key no I
just found it ironic that it sort of
ended with you pulled the trigger I just
thought it was funny
that's all you know after all this and
then yeah go for it
violence yes terrorism goes fear you
know so um yeah all of that is
performative but I just wanted to
highlight the l word I guess and the the
love there and say there's this cool
book but I still haven't really finished
reading it but I like the title and it's
called love is letting go of fear and
that's like the only thing that like
came up in my mind the entire time but I
also wanted to send out the normal
appreciation and gratitude for having
this conversation on the levels that you
did so thank you so much I have I'm
literally shaking inside saying this but
yeah thank you both of you
um and dude is it Hassan or is it Hudson
like can you please just I was I was
thinking that like these a little Arab
accent that I'm used to hearing across
I'm all right
Hassan God it's okay it's okay for me
dude like key is not real my real name
and I've had my name said a million
different ways so it's just funny I just
like bringing in your authentic name I
don't even think I say it right
sometimes but it's it's keeping uh it's
a that's the name it's a channel name
speaking of languages whoo languages
it's a good copy there yep and
awesome Tyson really bad I just want to
send my respect I really appreciate
Benjamin Hudson and everybody here
listening and I have so many things
coming up and so I'm getting that lesson
of like just rain it all in and put it
into action awesome great alright well
we'll wrap up there oh I keep forgetting
and on some of my other sessions so
stoah it runs on a gift economy so if if
anybody feels a sense of generosity and
want to express that you can always do
that at listo and CA the very bottom I
guess there's a little gift link or
something like that and yeah thanks to
thanks to Peter and the the stoah for
being creating a space for us a campfire
for us to explore a bit and and start to
to wade into the the waters of conflict
take care guys